<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>coronavirus on Keaan</title><link>https://www.keaan.co.uk/tags/coronavirus/</link><description>Recent content in coronavirus on Keaan</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 17 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.keaan.co.uk/tags/coronavirus/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Becoming a Leader</title><link>https://www.keaan.co.uk/2020/05/17/becomingaleader/</link><pubDate>Sun, 17 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.keaan.co.uk/2020/05/17/becomingaleader/</guid><description>This morning had my HLA Scholar Interview. Barely got my application off - saved by a timezone switch to GMT at month or so ago.
&amp;ldquo;What are you on about?&amp;rdquo; to paraphrase my father. Ah so, this is an opportunity to work with the Healthcare Leadership Academy. An organisation keen on training skills in leadership, project management and networking amongst healthcare professionals. Dr Johann Malawana, a obstetrician, previous junior doctor representative and now social entrepreneur is responsible for the organisation.</description></item><item><title>What's Next</title><link>https://www.keaan.co.uk/2020/04/12/athalftime/</link><pubDate>Sun, 12 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.keaan.co.uk/2020/04/12/athalftime/</guid><description>12th April
Yesterday was my 25th birthday. Yep, 25 years on Earth - or a quarter of my life already up as my parents put it. Its a pretty good time to be at home. Spring has arrived. Sun is out. Plenty of chocolate in the house. It&amp;rsquo;s also halftime for the degree. Lots of exciting things to look back on and build towards.
Led the Academic Medicine Society in my Second Year Summer Research Project in the Institute of Cancer Research at Newcastle University StaffBank Shifts at Epsom &amp;amp; St Helier.</description></item><item><title>Joining the Front-line</title><link>https://www.keaan.co.uk/2020/04/01/hcanews2/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.keaan.co.uk/2020/04/01/hcanews2/</guid><description>Monday 24th March
Day 1 of Lockdown has arrived.
All non-essential shops have now closed.
The seriousness of the situation has become clear.
Summer Research A week ago last Wednesday, I was rejected from my ICR Summer Research Project. The reason? Ultimately, this time we decided to go for another candidate that has already experience on the topic that we will be working on.
That ends my third ICR application in three years.</description></item><item><title>Coronavirus</title><link>https://www.keaan.co.uk/2020/03/23/coronavirushits/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.keaan.co.uk/2020/03/23/coronavirushits/</guid><description>Sunday 15th March
It is freezing. I can hear students walking in the street. Birds are chirping. Yep, I woke up in my car this morning. Halfway Ball was not very memorable funnily enough. The mother&amp;rsquo;s plan for lots of photos to be taken - may or may not be true.
I hurdle my way back home for a NEMSOC simulation day. All very exciting and daunting! Do I know my ABCs, prehospital escalation pathways.</description></item></channel></rss>