<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>reflection on Keaan</title><link>https://www.keaan.co.uk/tags/reflection/</link><description>Recent content in reflection on Keaan</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.keaan.co.uk/tags/reflection/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>OSCEs in Lockdown</title><link>https://www.keaan.co.uk/2021/01/14/endofy4part1/</link><pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.keaan.co.uk/2021/01/14/endofy4part1/</guid><description>January Examinations are over.
75 SBAs - Tuesday 5th January
75 questions on our entire medical clinical year curriculum so far. Some of the questions were really tough and even after a post-mortem discussion with housemates, didn&amp;rsquo;t really seem much clearer.
I do feel I have recognised a couple areas of weakness - liver and kidneys. As much as I prided myself on learning haematology and endocrinology to weird and wonderful complexity, this exam was really focused on common management considerations.</description></item><item><title>Why I Made this Blog</title><link>https://www.keaan.co.uk/2020/12/10/whyimadethisblog/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.keaan.co.uk/2020/12/10/whyimadethisblog/</guid><description>Blogs are so brilliantly relateable. How else are you gonna find someone going through the same of emotions and circumstances whilst you&amp;rsquo;re tucked up in your Lockdown Room sipping on Instant Cappucino. Long live the blog.
For me this, all began as I have a lot fire from my Biomedical Science degree. At lot of people counted me out including tutors. I just simply just wanted to get into Medicine. But if I didn&amp;rsquo;t and my tutors were somehow provided right, at least I would be thorough in documenting the reasons why.</description></item><item><title>Coronavirus</title><link>https://www.keaan.co.uk/2020/03/23/coronavirushits/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.keaan.co.uk/2020/03/23/coronavirushits/</guid><description>Sunday 15th March
It is freezing. I can hear students walking in the street. Birds are chirping. Yep, I woke up in my car this morning. Halfway Ball was not very memorable funnily enough. The mother&amp;rsquo;s plan for lots of photos to be taken - may or may not be true.
I hurdle my way back home for a NEMSOC simulation day. All very exciting and daunting! Do I know my ABCs, prehospital escalation pathways.</description></item><item><title>Mental Health</title><link>https://www.keaan.co.uk/2020/03/08/mentalhealth/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.keaan.co.uk/2020/03/08/mentalhealth/</guid><description>Friday 28th February
Back in Lanchester Road Hospital Education Centre. It is time for a day of teaching on Bipolar, Personality Disorders and Eating Disorders. Snacks and coffees are plentiful. Mental Health rotation has been very welcoming so far.
As has been the case so far, we&amp;rsquo;ve been taught some human psychology and sociology. Depression as a battle between stressors and resilience. Bipolar with percentage swings between high and low mood.</description></item><item><title>Undergraduate Oncology Conference</title><link>https://www.keaan.co.uk/2020/02/10/undergradoncology/</link><pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.keaan.co.uk/2020/02/10/undergradoncology/</guid><description>Friday Evening at 7pm. We&amp;rsquo;re off to Cambridge for a Poster Presentation at the Cambridge University Oncology Society Conference. Short delay at Peterborough provided enough time to join in the Academic Medicine Society Committee Video Call - plans for the Conference are being mapped out. Great to give back on some of my experiences from the year before to students now planning their first Conference. Otherwise, just flicking through Reproductive Health notes from the day before.</description></item><item><title>Building Societies</title><link>https://www.keaan.co.uk/2019/12/17/buildingsocieties/</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.keaan.co.uk/2019/12/17/buildingsocieties/</guid><description>Its the end of the first term of my first clinical year at Newastle University. Been exciting to get on the wards for the first time. Experience a close to full length day with nurses, junior doctors, core trainees and consultants in a variety of wards and departments. Different places, different people, different ward-based cultures.
And now as the Christmas break begins, its also a time to catch-up on society events planning - Academic Medicine Society, Haematology-Oncology Society and Emergency Medicine Society.</description></item><item><title>MOSLER Time</title><link>https://www.keaan.co.uk/2019/10/30/weekinlife-copy/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.keaan.co.uk/2019/10/30/weekinlife-copy/</guid><description>Its Reading Week! In seven years of university, never had anything like this. So why not return home - kick back and relax and run over some people on Grand Theft Auto V! And once we&amp;rsquo;re happy with that, how about a time to reflect.
Monday 21st October 2019:
Its MOSLER day. Our first ever Modified Objective Structured Long Examination Review - just as daunting as it sounds. But to take-away my nerves before my 11am timeslot, I decided to head to the base ward - Elderly Care.</description></item><item><title>Week in the Life</title><link>https://www.keaan.co.uk/2019/10/06/weekinlife/</link><pubDate>Sun, 06 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.keaan.co.uk/2019/10/06/weekinlife/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;strong>Monday&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Its Monday quiz time! Fared better than the GI quiz two weeks ago. Pleased with my performance. Skin condition management is still blurry. Will improve this soon!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Clinical skills in the afternoon features subcutaneous and intramuscular injections as well as a good old return to catheter preparation. Both were rather solid. Feeling better about my aseptic technique. Still one to practice on dummies rather than patients at this stage!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Midnight tonight is the deadline for the Pathology Society essay. With a bare-bones plan and grand total of 0 words, its time to sprint off to the Walton Library for any book inspiration (sadly none) before a downtown trip to the University Study Rooms with a bottle of Summer Fruits Oasis. The 1,000 word essay was complete 40 minutes before the deadline. This essay was really good practise for a change in my writing style - becoming more descriptive, fluent and easy to read. Avoiding hefty jargon and sticking to the expectations of what&amp;rsquo;s being asked of you. This was a fulfilling essay to write. With more dedicated time, very assured I will be able to be really competitive in academic writing.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Fear of Failure</title><link>https://www.keaan.co.uk/2019/07/16/fearoffailure/</link><pubDate>Tue, 16 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.keaan.co.uk/2019/07/16/fearoffailure/</guid><description>&lt;p>We are officially two-thirds into this nine year projected voyage through university. That means just three years left to complete some goals. The next one - a first author publication.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>OSCE Voyage</title><link>https://www.keaan.co.uk/2019/05/16/endofy2/</link><pubDate>Thu, 16 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.keaan.co.uk/2019/05/16/endofy2/</guid><description>With sincere apologies for the delay, please find attached a letter outlining the outcome of your Research Scholarship application.
Brilliant. A pit of sheer despair in my stomach. I have to read a letter of rejection now. But&amp;hellip;.
The Panel was impressed with your application and consequently has decided to offer you a Research Scholarship for your project entitled: “Classification of Patients with Acute Lymphoblastic Leukaemia into Clinically Applicable Genetic Subgroups through Machine Learning Enabling Delivery of Precision Medicine”</description></item><item><title>Back on the Bike</title><link>https://www.keaan.co.uk/2019/02/04/backonthebike/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.keaan.co.uk/2019/02/04/backonthebike/</guid><description>&lt;p>The sun is out. Springtime in Newcastle has never seemingly looked so good in early February.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Dealing with the Off the Field</title><link>https://www.keaan.co.uk/2018/11/25/offthefield/</link><pubDate>Sun, 25 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.keaan.co.uk/2018/11/25/offthefield/</guid><description>&lt;p>We are now onto Case 18 in pre-clinical programme at Newcastle University. This week we&amp;rsquo;re learning about Malaria and Global Health. Learning about diseases that we may never see clinically in the UK but are likely to in other areas of the world. Its new and different so learning in second year feels fresh and exciting.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Being Useful</title><link>https://www.keaan.co.uk/2018/11/09/beinguseful/</link><pubDate>Fri, 09 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.keaan.co.uk/2018/11/09/beinguseful/</guid><description>&lt;p>Second year of medicine at Newcastle is now just under two weeks away! A long summer to reflect and think about the future - those professional, social and academic goals. It feels strange to think about being on the &amp;lsquo;back nine&amp;rsquo; of your university experience (sixth year of a projected nine) but having now had the journey of being a first year medical student, it really is still all to play for.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Rejection, Interview #2, ___</title><link>https://www.keaan.co.uk/2017/08/17/rejection4-copy/</link><pubDate>Thu, 17 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.keaan.co.uk/2017/08/17/rejection4-copy/</guid><description>&lt;p>Two days ago, I received an invitation to an interview for 2017 Entry from Newcastle. This is for the five year programme having originally applied to them earlier this year.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Rejection 4</title><link>https://www.keaan.co.uk/2017/03/30/rejection4/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.keaan.co.uk/2017/03/30/rejection4/</guid><description>&lt;p>Southampton rejection pre-interview.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Rejection 2</title><link>https://www.keaan.co.uk/2017/01/13/rejection2/</link><pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.keaan.co.uk/2017/01/13/rejection2/</guid><description>&lt;p>Tough but expected. From Newcastle. Likely a low UKCAT score.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It is deflating but nothing new that I can&amp;rsquo;t cope with.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Rejection 1</title><link>https://www.keaan.co.uk/2016/12/22/rejection1/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.keaan.co.uk/2016/12/22/rejection1/</guid><description>Well it has been coming. In my gut, felt as if I did not perform as well as I would have liked at my Plymouth interview. Combination of nerves and inability to express myself through past experiences did not help. I did feel as if I coped better with the ethical scenario that Plymouth allow you to devote time to prepare beforehand but for the impromptu ethical situations, I could not think as laterally or quickly as I would have liked.</description></item></channel></rss>